{"tossups": [{"question": "This man appointed George Creel to head the Committee on Public Information, a propaganda machine. He attacked those who \u201cpoured the poison of disloyalty\u201d in a State of the Union address, but was unable to get a press-censorship clause in the Espionage Act. For ten points, name this President who reneged on a campaign promise to \u201ckeep us out of the War\u201d by committing American forces to World War I.", "answer": "Woodrow<b> Wilson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This person\u2019s life savings were swindled by two men who claimed to have gold from a distant relative. This spy for the Union during the Raid on Combahee Ferry had biographies written by Sarah Hopkins Bradford, which described her navigating a network of tunnels and safehouses. For ten points, name this abolitionist who escorted slaves as they escaped on the Underground Railroad.", "answer": "Harriet<b> Tubman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This figure was guarded by a group of horsemen called the Celeres, and he may be associated with the war god Quirinus because of his disappearance near the Quirinal Hill. He proclaimed \u201cso perish every one hereafter that will leap over my wall\u201d while killing his brother after they debated the meaning of the number of birds flying around their heads. For ten points, name this brother of Remus, the first king of the Romans.", "answer": "<b> Romulus</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 2003, a copy of this painting was covered by a blue curtain while Colin Powell addressed the United Nations. On the left side of this painting, a bull stands over a woman who is holding her dead child. An eye-shaped light bulb explodes in this painting above an impaled, screaming horse. For ten points, name this painting inspired by the bombing of the title Basque town, a massive painting by Pablo Picasso.", "answer": "<b> Guernica</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man directed a 2005 film where he played Fred Friendly, a colleague of Edward Murrow, as well as a 2014 film about the recovery of art in Nazi Germany. This director of<em> Good Night and Good Luck</em> and<em> The Monuments Men</em> operates a project to monitor Sudanese war crimes via satellite imagery. For ten points, name this American actor who starred as Daniel Ocean in the<em> Ocean\u2019s 11</em> trilogy and with Sandra Bullock in 2013\u2019s<em> Gravity</em>.", "answer": "George<b> Clooney</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This ruler attempted to establish the Kingdom of Livonia as a vassal state, and this ruler established his country\u2019s first printing press at Kitai-gorod. This ruler conquered Kazan and Astrakhan, and he established a secret police force known as the Oprichniki. Feodor I succeeded this ruler after he killed his eldest son in a fit of rage, eventually leading to the Time of Troubles. For ten points, name this first Tsar of Russia whose epithet notes his power, not his cruelty.", "answer": "<b> Ivan IV</b> of Russia [or<b> Ivan the Terrible</b>; or<b> Ivan Grozny</b>] <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The price elasticity of this quantity should always be negative, but Veblen goods violate that theory. John Maynard Keynes argued that, in recessions, the aggregate of this quantity should be bolstered by government spending. During the Irish Potato Famine, this quantity rose for potatoes even as their price rose, as people could no longer afford luxuries like meat. For ten points, name this economic quantity that, in competitive markets, should reach equilibrium with supply.", "answer": "<b> demand</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {"question": "The inefficient Trabant was built in this former country. It used distinctive Ampelm\u00a8annchen crosswalk symbols that are now enjoyed as its modern residents experience \u201cOstalgie.\u201d Its residents were once spied on by the Markus Wolf-led Stasi, which revealed its records after reunification in 1990. For ten points, name this former Soviet-zone country with capital Berlin.", "answer": "<b> East Germany</b> (accept<b> G</b>erman<b> D</b>emocratic<b> R</b>epublic; or<b> D</b>eutsche<b> D</b>emokratische<b> R</b>epublik; do not accept or prompt on Germany)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During this event, paratroopers captured bridges on the River Orne and Saint-M`ere-\u00b4Eglise. The First US Army Group participated in Operation Quicksilver prior to this campaign, and was commanded by General Patton. The Canadians were supposed to capture Caen during this operation, and the Americans were assigned to Fortress Cherbourg, part of the Atlantic Wall. For ten points, name this operation, an Allied landing on five beaches in Northern France.", "answer": "Operation<b> Overlord</b> (accept<b> D-Day</b>, accept Battle of<b> Normandy</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Giotto Probe flew through the coma of this object in 1986, which will be visible again in 2061. For ten points, name this comet that approaches Earth roughly every 76 years.", "answer": "<b> Halley</b>\u2019s comet [or 1P/<b>Halley</b>]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {"question": "Kate Altman\u2019s testimony of this event was discredited after one lawyer asked her to repeat her version multiple times. Frances Perkins was sent to investigate this event, for which Max Blanck and Isaac Harris stood trial for locking exit doors from the outside, leading to the deaths of 146 workers. For ten points, name this 1911 disaster in a New York garment factory.", "answer": "<b> Triangle Shirtwaist</b> Factory fire", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A portion of this structure was built in the contested Ordos region. The early heqin [huh-CHEEN] system allowed the Xiongnu [tchee-ONG-noo] to rule the area north of this structure. The Jiayu Pass serves as the end of one section of this structure built by the Ming dynasty to defend against Mongol attacks. For ten points, name this massive series of Chinese defensive fortifications.", "answer": "<b> Great Wall</b> of China", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In a letter to John Holmes, Thomas Jefferson commented that this law had \u201cawakened and filled me with terror.\u201d James Tallmadge unsuccessfully proposed that this law make</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>children of slaves free after reaching 25 years old. It was overturned by the (*)</b> Kansas-Nebraska Act and ruled unconstitutional in<em> Dred Scott v. Sanford</em>. For ten points, name this 1820 compromise that banned slavery in certain regions of the Louisiana Purchase, except in a namesake state.", "answer": "<b> Missouri Compromise</b> (accept<b> Compromise of 1820</b> before that year is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man was thought to be aboard a plane carrying the Bolivian president in 2013, but he had not left Sheremetyevo Airport since arriving there from Hong Kong. This former employee of (+) Booz Allen Hamilton was attempting to avoid extradition to the U.S. after leaking sensitive (*)</b> documents to Glenn Greenwald. For ten points, name this man who in June 2013 revealed the extent of U.S. government surveillance programs such as PRISM.", "answer": "Edward Joseph<b> Snowden</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>James Monroe vouched for this man\u2019s U.S. citizenship, freeing him from French prison. He was sued for libel after writing a response to Edmund Burke\u2019s</b><em><b> Reflections on the</b></em><b> (+) </b> <em><b>Revolution in France</b></em><b>, and he criticized organized religion and the divinity of the Bible while advocating for the rise of deism in</b><em><b> The (*) </b></em> <b>Age of Reason</b>. The absurdity of an island ruling a continent was observed by, for ten points, what early American revolutionary thinker in his 1776 pamphlet<em> Common Sense</em>?", "answer": "Thomas<b> Paine</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>This adjective names a white supremacist \u201cCouncil of Citizens\u201d led by Earl Holt. Brent Bozell ghostwrote a book for Arizona Senator Barry Goldwater about</b><em><b> The Conscience of</b></em> <b>this type of person. The Canadian Alliance (+)</b> <b>merged with another party to form the</b> <b>Canadian political party of this name, which was, until October 2015, led by Stephen (*) </b>Harper. Traditional cultural institutions are supported by, for ten points, what political philosophy that describes the American Republican Party, contrasted with \u201cliberalism\u201d?", "answer": "<b> conservative</b> (accept word forms; do not accept conservationist or its word forms)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Livy claims that one participant in this conflict used heated vinegar to cross a blocked mountain pass. Quintus Fabius was nicknamed \u201cthe delayer\u201d during this conflict for refusing to engage in battle. One side in this conflict lost at (+) Lake Trasimene [trah-sih-meh-nee] but later won the decisive victory on the plains of Zama under Scipio [SKIP-ee-oh], counteracting a devastating loss at Cannae [CANN-aye]. The (*) </b> Alps were traversed by Hannibal during, for ten points, what second of a series of conflicts between Rome and Carthage?", "answer": "<b> 2nd Punic</b> War (prompt on Punic War(s)) Page 8", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A second investigation of this event was chaired by Ramsey Clark. The most complete</b> <b>recording of this event was sold to Life Magazine for $150,000 by Abraham (+)</b> <b>Zapruder.</b> <b>John Connally was seriously wounded during this event, which was performed from the sixth floor of the (*) </b> Texas School Book Depository. Jack Ruby killed the perpetrator of this event before he could stand trial. For ten points, name this event in which Lee Harvey Oswald shot the 35th president of the United States.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> of<b> J</b>ohn Fitzgerald<b> Kennedy</b> (accept<b> JFK</b> for Kennedy; prompt on partial answers; do not accept assassination of Robert Kennedy)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This city\u2019s empire defeated Ercole d\u2019Este to conquer Commachio and defeated a rival in the War of Chioggia. It was targeted by the League of (+) Cambrai, founded by its nemesis Julius II. Its Arsenale was said to be able to produce one (*)</b> warship a day. A fleet from this city was led by Enrico Dandolo in the Fourth Crusade and sacked Constantinople. For ten points, name this \u201cMost Serene Republic\u201d which was ruled by doges.", "answer": "Most Serene Republic of<b> Venice</b>  (1) <b>According to Tarikh al-Sudan, this empire\u2019s last ruler was Mahmud IV, whose</b> <b>defeat at the Battle of Djenne caused its collapse. The ton-tigi, or \u201cquiver-masters,\u201d</b> <b>advised this empire\u2019s rulers at its (+)</b> <b>Gbara legislature. Its constitution, the</b> <b>Kouroukan Fouga, was established after its first ruler won the Battle of Kirina. This</b> <b>empire\u2019s most famous ruler (*)</b> caused inflation by spending tons of gold on his way to Mecca. For ten points, name this West African empire led by Sundieta Keita and Mansa Musa. ANSWER:<b> Mali Empire</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}